<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://healthcare.ai/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://healthcare.ai/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://healthcare.ai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-12-09T06:33:39-07:00</updated><id>http://healthcare.ai//</id><title type="html">healthcare.ai</title><entry><title type="html">Benefits of machine learning in healthcare</title><link href="http://healthcare.ai/blog/2016/12/05/benefits-of-machine-learning-in-healthcare/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Benefits of machine learning in healthcare" /><published>2016-12-05T07:24:23-07:00</published><updated>2016-12-05T07:24:23-07:00</updated><id>http://healthcare.ai/blog/2016/12/05/benefits-of-machine-learning-in-healthcare</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://healthcare.ai/blog/2016/12/05/benefits-of-machine-learning-in-healthcare/">&lt;p&gt;If you read much about technology, you have likely heard about machine learning, but may be wondering how it would work in healthcare. Where’s the low-hanging fruit? And how could it help my clinical team?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, we’ll be practical in our discussion. Throughout healthcare, and many other industries, there are heuristics (or rules of thumb) that help people make decisions. A popular example in healthcare is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2845681/&quot;&gt;LACE index&lt;/a&gt;, which provides a likelihood of patient 30-day readmission risk. You might have also heard of similar tools like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/194262&quot;&gt;SOFA Score&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJM200102153440701#t=article&quot;&gt;Apgar Score&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2999700/&quot;&gt;PRISM Score&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2999700/&quot;&gt;PIM Score&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most of these scores, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.besler.com/lace-risk-score/&quot;&gt;LACE calculation&lt;/a&gt; is fairly simple. It’s based on length of stay, acuity of the admission, patient comorbities, and ED visits within the last six months. In each of these categories, points are assigned–a length of stay of three days equals three points, for example. Then the points from each categories are added up to form the LACE index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s simple and indicative of how healthcare has worked for the last 20-30 years. First, there’s a national study, which eventually leads to guidelines and a simple calculation to help prioritize which patients are most at risk of something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s wrong with that? Well, the guidelines can only be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2845681/&quot;&gt;narrowly applied&lt;/a&gt; and even then &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4670852/&quot;&gt;don’t give impressive results&lt;/a&gt;. Think of it–LACE was developed from patients seen in Ontario from 2004-2008. Do your patient demographics closely match those in Ontario? Or, do your patient demographics even match your same set from ten years ago? Perhaps not. Another issue is applicability–since LACE requires the patient’s length of stay, the score is only available upon discharge. What if you want a risk score early during their stay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a some of the reasons that machine learning is fantastic. First it learns the important relationships in your data on past patients and their outcomes. This means that the model is customized on your data from the last few years–you don’t have to rely on scores made on other populations, 10-20 years ago. In addition, machine learning allows one to create a model based on whatever data is available when you need a risk score (ie, upon admission rather than discharge).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, what does this customized model provide? Accurate risk scores, enabling confident and precise resource allocation, leading to lower costs and improved outcomes. As an added bonus, &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthcare.ai/&quot;&gt;healthcare.ai&lt;/a&gt; is focused on providing guidance as to why a risk score was high, such that the the clinician not only knows who’s most at risk, but also can quickly see what can be done to lower that patient’s risk. We’ll detail this ability in a future post. Thanks, and please &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthcare.ai/contact&quot;&gt;reach out&lt;/a&gt; with any questions or comments!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="overview" /><summary type="html">If you read much about technology, you have likely heard about machine learning, but may be wondering how it would work in healthcare. Where’s the low-hanging fruit? And how could it help my clinical team?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why R and Python?</title><link href="http://healthcare.ai/blog/2016/12/02/why-r-and-python/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why R and Python?" /><published>2016-12-02T07:17:06-07:00</published><updated>2016-12-02T07:17:06-07:00</updated><id>http://healthcare.ai/blog/2016/12/02/why-r-and-python</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://healthcare.ai/blog/2016/12/02/why-r-and-python/">&lt;p&gt;As time goes on, this blog will touch on many of the technical choices made at Health Catalyst. It will mostly focus on data science. If there’s a particular topic that interests, &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthcare.ai/contact.html&quot;&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt;! Some posts will be short, while others will be in-depth. The tone will be informal, with a focus on content and frequent posts (twice per-week) rather than polish. When we talk about doing things with data, we’ll post the code, so you can follow along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doing healthcare machine learning, why’d we choice R and Python? To be honest, this decision wasn’t that complicated. Of course, there are a lot of fantastic statistical tools available today besides just R and Python: Matlab, SAS, Stata, SPSS, and others. While languages like Java, C++, and C# are great, they’re &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compiled_language&quot;&gt;compiled&lt;/a&gt;, which makes them difficult to use for data analysis. We had just a few criteria when narrowing down the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was it open-source?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Could it do breadth and depth?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did it have wide support?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted something open-source, because free is obviously great, but also because we wanted to be able to contribute to the same community. Data literacy is important to getting started in most professional careers, and it’s fantastic how free tools have democratized entry into many fields over the last decade–we want to support that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R and Python are the obvious open-source options when playing with data, but how are they on breadth and depth as well as community support? Actually pretty fantastic. Python is often known as the Swiss Army knife of programming languages–it can support machine learning, web development, web scraping, desktop applications, etc. It also supports these things well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While R is more narrowly focused on statistics compared to Python, it is also great at several things. First, it offers well-documented algorithms and tools for &lt;a href=&quot;https://cran.r-project.org/web/views/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;whatever&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; you want to do in statistics. Second, it has fantastic &lt;a href=&quot;http://tutorials.iq.harvard.edu/R/Rgraphics/Rgraphics.html&quot;&gt;visualization software&lt;/a&gt; (better than Python, it could be argued), and thirdly it is great at professional &lt;a href=&quot;http://yihui.name/knitr/&quot;&gt;document generation&lt;/a&gt; for both reports and data education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of support, here’s a plot showing the popularity of each of these languages over time on &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/&quot;&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt;, a popular Q and A site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/LanguageComparisonOverTime.png&quot; alt=&quot;Popularity Plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are many other options for doing statistics in healthcare, R and Python are among the very best, and we’re excited to use them to improve patient care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: We obtained data using &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.stackexchange.com/stackoverflow/query/589066/language-trends-questions-per-tag-per-month&quot;&gt;this tool&lt;/a&gt;; we &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/levithatcher/130ee5d6586839ceeb3975e0afee9b65&quot;&gt;plotted using R&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="overview" /><summary type="html">As time goes on, this blog will touch on many of the technical choices made at Health Catalyst. It will mostly focus on data science. If there’s a particular topic that interests, contact us! Some posts will be short, while others will be in-depth. The tone will be informal, with a focus on content and frequent posts (twice per-week) rather than polish. When we talk about doing things with data, we’ll post the code, so you can follow along.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to healthcare.ai</title><link href="http://healthcare.ai/blog/2016/12/01/welcome-to-healthcareai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to healthcare.ai" /><published>2016-12-01T08:37:13-07:00</published><updated>2016-12-01T08:37:13-07:00</updated><id>http://healthcare.ai/blog/2016/12/01/welcome-to-healthcareai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://healthcare.ai/blog/2016/12/01/welcome-to-healthcareai/">&lt;p&gt;Health Catalyst’s data science team is excited to present &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthcare.ai/&quot;&gt;healthcare.ai&lt;/a&gt;. This ambitious new project offers healthcare-specific machine learning packages, as well as analysis, commentary, and advice on leveraging machine learning within any health system, regardless of size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While companies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://research.google.com/teams/brain/healthcare/&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://searchhealthit.techtarget.com/opinion/Microsoft-Project-Adam-may-reach-healthcare-specialties&quot;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mskcc.org/about/innovative-collaborations/watson-oncology&quot;&gt;IBM&lt;/a&gt; are doing machine learning on the outskirts of healthcare, we work from the center. We bring practical, accurate predictive models to health systems interested in improving their operational, financial, and clinical efficiencies. First and foremost, we want to improve patient outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning has been used in other industries for years, but healthcare is late to the game. We want to change this. Considering the enormous amount of data in EMRs, the impressive ability of machine learning to detect complex patterns, and the thousands of &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.lww.com/journalpatientsafety/Fulltext/2013/09000/A_New,_Evidence_based_Estimate_of_Patient_Harms.2.aspx&quot;&gt;lives at risk&lt;/a&gt; in hospitals each day, it’s imperative to help healthcare organizations use data to make better decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of health systems hiring expensive data scientists to do this work, we want to help anyone interested in healthcare data—BI Developers and SQL-based folks in particular—develop machine learning skills (via R or Python).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll share more details about healthcare.ai in the coming weeks, but here’s a snapshot of what it encompasses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A healthcare-specific R machine learning package.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A healthcare-specific Python machine learning package&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guidance on where and how to apply machine learning in healthcare.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analysis on outcomes improvement via CAFE, the largest healthcare dataset ever compiled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get started with healthcare machine learning now, see &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthcare.ai/&quot;&gt;healthcare.ai&lt;/a&gt; for R and Python.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Levi Thatcher</name></author><category term="overview" /><summary type="html">Health Catalyst’s data science team is excited to present healthcare.ai. This ambitious new project offers healthcare-specific machine learning packages, as well as analysis, commentary, and advice on leveraging machine learning within any health system, regardless of size.</summary></entry></feed>
